Today I'm going to unpack for you
سأقوم اليوم بتفكيك
three examples of iconic design,
ثلاثة أمثلة عن التصميم الأيقوني،
and it makes perfect sense
و من المنطقي جدا
that I should be the one to do it
أن أكون أنا الشخص المناسب للقيام بذلك
because I have a Bachelor's degree in Literature.
لأني أحمل شهادة البكالوريوس في الأدب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I'm also a famous
لكنني أيضا مشهور
minor television personality
بكوني شخصية تلفزيونية بسيطة
and an avid collector of
ولكوني مُجَّمع هاوٍ
Design Within Reach catalogs,
لفهارس "التصميم في متناول الجميع"،
so I pretty much know
وبالتالي فأنا أعرف إلى حد كبير
everything there is.
كل شيء بهذا الخصوص.
Now, I'm sure you
الآن، أنا متأكد أنكم
recognize this object;
تعرفون هذا الشئ؛
many of you probably saw it
الكثير منكم على الأرجح قد رآه
as you were landing your private zeppelins
وأنتم تهبطون بمناطيد زبلين الخاصة بكم
at Los Angeles International Airport
في مطار لوس انجليس الدولي
over the past couple of days.
خلال الأيام الماضية.
This is known as the Theme Building;
هذا يعرف على أنه "بناء الموضوع"؛
that is its name for reasons
هذا هو إسمه لأسباب
that are still very murky.
لا تزال غامضة جدا.
And it is perhaps
وهو ربما
the best example we have in Los Angeles
أفضل مثال لدينا في لوس انجليس
of ancient extraterrestrial architecture.
على الهندسة المعمارية العتيقة من خارج الأرض.
It was first excavated in 1961
تم التنقيب عنه لأول مرة سنة 1961
as they were building LAX,
حين كان يتم بناء مطار لوس أنجليس،
although scientists believe that
على الرغم من أن العلماء يعتقدون أن
it dates back to the year 2000
تاريخه يرجع إلى سنة 2000
Before Common Era,
قبل الميلاد،
when it was used as
عندما كانت يستخدم
a busy transdimensional space port
كميناء فضائي مزدحم عابر للأبعاد
by the ancient astronauts
من قبل رواد الفضاء القدماء
who first colonized this planet
الذين استعمروا هذا الكوكب أولا
and raised our species
وارتفعوا بصنفنا
from savagery by giving us
من الهمجية بإعطائنا
the gift of written language
هبة اللغة المكتوبة
and technology and
والتكنولوجيا
the gift of revolving restaurants.
وهبة المطاعم الدوارة.
It is thought to have been
ويعتقد أنه كان يوجد
a replacement for the older space ports
بديل للموانئ الفضائية الأقدم
located, of course, at Stonehenge
والتي تقع، بطبيعة الحال، في ستونهنج
and considered to be
وتعتبر
quite an improvement
تحسنا إلى حد كبير
due to the uncluttered design,
نظرا للتصميم المرتب،
the lack of druids hanging around all the time
لعدم وجود كهنة يتسكعون طوال الوقت
and obviously, the much better
وبالطبع، وصول أفضل
access to parking.
إلى مواقف السيارات.
When it was uncovered,
عندما تم الكشف عنه،
it ushered in a new era
بشّر بعهد جديد
of streamlined, archaically futuristic design
من التصميم المستقبلي المبسط على نحو بال
called Googie,
يدعى غوغي،
which came to be synonymous with
والذي صار مرادفا
the Jet Age, a misnomer.
لعصر الطائرة النفاثة، تسمية خاطئة.
After all, the ancient astronauts who used it
مع ذلك، رواد الفضاء القدماء الذين استخدموه
did not travel by jet very often,
لم يسافروا على متن طائرة نفاثة في كثير من الأحيان،
preferring instead to travel by feathered serpent
بل معظمهم فضل اللجوء للسفر بواسطة ثعبان مريّش
powered by crystal skulls.
مدعوم بجماجم الكريستال.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Ah yes, a table.
آه نعم، طاولة.
We use these every day.
نستخدم هذه كل يوم.
And on top of it,
وفوقها،
the juicy salif.
عاصر الليمون.
This is a design by Philippe Starck,
هذا تصميم لفيليب ستارك،
who I believe is in the audience at this very moment.
والذي أعتقد أنه موجود في الحضور في هذه اللحظة بالذات.
And you can tell it is a Starck design
ويمكنك معرفة أنه تصميم لستارك
by its precision, its playfulness,
بدقته ولعوبيته،
its innovation and
من ابتكاره
its promise of imminent violence.
وإيحائه بعنف وشيك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It is a design that challenges your intuition --
إنه تصميم يتحدى حدسكم --
it is not what you think it is when you first see it.
إنه ليس ما تعتقده حين تراه لأول مرة.
It is not a fork designed
إنها ليست بشوكة مصممة
to grab three hors d'oeuvres at a time,
للإمساك بثلاثة مقبلات في آن واحد،
which would be useful out in the lobby,
والذي يمكن أن يكون مفيدا خارجا في الردهة،
I would say.
يمكنني القول.
And despite its obvious
وعلى الرغم من واضح
influence by the ancient astronauts
تأثير رواد الفضاء القدماء
and its space agey-ness and tripodism,
فضائية عمره وقوائمه الثلاثة،
it is not something
هو ليس بشئ
designed to attach to your brain
مصمم للالتصاق بدماغك
and suck out your thoughts.
وامتصاص أفكارك.
It is in fact a citrus juicer
هو في الحقيقة عصارة ليمون
and when I say that,
وعندما أقول ذلك،
you never see it as anything else again.
أنت لن تراه كأي شيء آخر مجددا.
It is also not a monument to design,
وهو كذلك ليس بنصب تذكاري للتصميم،
it is a monument to design's utility.
إنه نصب تذكاري لنفعية التصميم.
You can take it home with you,
بإمكانك أخذها للبيت معك،
unlike the Theme Building,
على خلاف "بناء الموضوع"،
which will stay where it is forever.
والذي سيبقى حيث هو إلى الأبد.
This is affordable
هذا في المتناول
and can come home with you
ويمكنه أن يعود معك إلى البيت
and, as such, it can sit
وعلى هذا النحو يمكنه أن يجلس
on your kitchen counter --
على طاولة المطبخ --
it can't go in your drawers;
لا يمكن أن يوضع في أدراجك؛
trust me, I found that out the hard way --
ثق بي، لقد اكتشفت ذلك بالطريقة الصعبة --
and make your kitchen counter into
واجعل من طاولة المطبخ الخاص بك
a monument to design.
نصبا تذكاريا للتصميم.
One other thing about it,
شيء آخر حول هذا الموضوع،
if you do have one at home,
إن كان لديك واحد في المنزل،
let me tell you one of the features you may not know:
دعوني أخبركم عن أحد الميزات التي قد لا تعرفونها:
when you fall asleep,
عندما تغفو،
it comes alive
يصبح حياً
and it walks around your house
ويمشي حول منزلك
and goes through your mail
ويفتش في بريدك
and watches you as you sleep.
ويراقبك وأنت نائم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Okay, what is this object?
حسنا، ما هو هذا الشيء؟
I have no idea. I don't know what that thing is.
ليس لدي فكرة. أنا لا أعرف ما هذا الشيء .
It looks terrible. Is it a little hot plate?
إنه يبدو رهيبا. هل هي لوحة ساخنة صغيرة؟
I don't get it.
لست أفهم الأمر.
Does anyone know? Chi?
هل يعرف أحدكم؟ تشي؟
It's an ... iPhone. iPhone.
إنه ... آيفون. آيفون.
Oh yes, that's right, I remember those;
أوه نعم، هذا صحيح، وأنا أتذكر ذلك؛
I had my whole bathroom tiles
كنت قد أجريت على بلاط حمامي بكامله
redone with those back in the good old days.
عملية إعادة تبليط باستخدام تلك في الأيام الخوالي.
No, I have an iPhone. Of course I do.
لا، لدي آيفون. بالطبع لدي.
Here is my well-loved iPhone.
هذا هو آيفوني المحبوب.
I do so many things on this little device.
أقوم بالكثير من الأمور على هذا الجهاز الصغير.
I like to read books on it.
أنا أحب قراءة الكتب عليه.
More than that, I like to buy books on it
أكثر من ذلك، أحب شراء الكتب عليه
that I never have to feel guilty about not reading
حيث أنني لست مضطرا أبدا للشعور بالذنب حول عدم قراءتها
because they go in here and I never look at them again
لأنها تذهب إلى هنا حيث لا أنظر إليها مجددا
and it's perfect.
والأمر مثالي.
I use it every day to
أستخدمه كل يوم
measure the weight of an ox,
لقياس وزن ثور،
for example.
على سبيل المثال.
Every now and then,
بين الحين والآخر،
I admit that I complete
أعترف بأنني أكمل
a phone call on it occasionally.
مكالمة هاتفية عن ذلك في بعض الأحيان.
And yet I forget about it all the time.
ولا أزال أنساه دائماً.
This is a design
هذا هو التصميم
that once you saw it,
الذي إذا شاهدته مرة،
you forgot about it.
تنساه بسرعة.
It is easy to forget the gasp-inducement
فمن السهل أن ننسى لحظات الإغراء
that occurred in 2007 when you first
التي حدثت سنة 2007 حين، ولأول مرة،
touched this thing because it became
لمستم هذا الشيء لأنه صار
so quickly pervasive
متفشيا بسرعة
and because of how instantly
وبسبب مدى فورية
we adopted these gestures
تبنينا لهذه الحركات
and made it an extension of our life.
وجعلناها امتدادا لحياتنا.
Unlike the Theme Building,
وخلافا لـ "بناء الموضوع"،
this is not alien technology.
هذه ليست تكنولوجيا دخيلة.
Or I should say,
أو ينبغي أن أقول،
what it did was it took technology
ما فعلته هو أنها أخذت التكنولوجيا
which, unlike people in this room,
والتي، على عكس الأشخاص الموجودين هنا،
to many other people in the world,
والعديد من الأشخاص الآخرين في العالم،
still feels very alien,
لا تزال تشعِر بغرابة شديدة،
and made it immediately and instantly feel
وجعلتها وبشكل مباشر وفوري تعطي شعورا
familiar and intimate.
بالحميمية والألفة.
And unlike the juicy salif,
وعلى خلاف عصارة الليمون،
it does not threaten
فهي لا تهدد
to attach itself to your brain,
بربط ذاتها بدماغكم،
rather, it simply
وإنما ببساطة
attaches itself to your brain.
تربط ذاتها بدماغكم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And you didn't even notice it happened.
وأنتم لم تلاحظوا حتى حدوثها.
So there you go. My name is John Hodgman.
وهذا كل شيء. إسمي جون هودجمان.
I just explained design.
وقد شرحت للتو التصميم.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)